Cutting, Edith; Papers ua902.001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Edith Cutting Papers
1938-1977
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Cutting, Edith E.
ua902.001
1.0 cubic ft.
Cutting was a folklorist, author, 1938 graduate of State College for Teachers, and a high school English teacher in Johnson City, New York.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Edith Cutting.
Biographical History
Edith Cutting was born March 31, 1918 at Elizabethtown, New York. She graduated from Elizabethtown High School in 1933, and from the New York State College for Teachers at Albany in 1938, where she received the degree of Bachelor of Science in Librarianship. She held numerous positions as librarian or English teacher, or both until her retirement in 1975. In 1941 she began work at Cornell University towards a Masters' degree, completing it in the summer of 1945.
As Miss Cutting was deeply interested in New York folklore, most of the materials in this collection are manuscripts dealing with this subject or correspondence relating to her publishing endeavors in the realm of folklore. Also there are some papers dealing with her teaching career annual reports, contracts, etc. The collection is rounded out with letters, and two scrapbooks dealing with all phases of her interest in folklore. There is also one bound folder filled with clippings, and two high school year books.
Scope and Contents
Includes correspondence, manuscripts, and other materials relating to the career of Miss Cutting and her interest in New York folklore. Of particular interest is the correspondence with Dr. Harold Thompson. Alo included are scrapbooks filled with clippings, letters, etc., giving insight into Miss Cutting's dual career as a folklorist and teacher.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged alphabetically.
Folklore; Folklore -- New York (State); UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Cutting, Edith E.; Thompson, Harold William, 1891-1964.
- Annual Reports: English Department Johnson City High School, Johnson City, New York, 1950-1972 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence: family (Includes one letter from Louis circa Jones, New York area folklorist and historian), 1944; 1977 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Harold W. Thompson, 1944-1958 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 3)
- Manuscript: "The Codex Sinaiticus.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 4)
- Manuscript: "The Douglass Manuscript" - article., Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 5)
- Manuscript: The Douglas Manuscript - E. Cutting M.A Thesis, Folder A. pp. 1-175, 1945 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 6)
- Manuscript: The Douglas Manuscript - thesis, Folder B. pp. 176-297, 1945 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 7)
- Manuscript: The Douglas Manuscript - thesis, unpaginated notes following pp. 297, ca. 1945 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 8)
- Manuscript: "I called this talk 'American folklore ...'", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 9)
- Manuscript: Johnson City Our Local Heritage., Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 10)
- Manuscript: Lore of an Adirondack County., Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 11)
- Manuscript: "More Lore.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 12)
- Manuscript: "New York Folklore Society.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 13)
- Manuscript: "Peter Carrott.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 14)
- Manuscript: "Society and folklore in the Champlain Valley.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 15)
- Manuscript: Quilt for Bermuda., Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 16)
- Manuscript: "Whistling Girls and Jumping Sheep.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous: notes, workshop programs, etc., Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 18)
- Publication: "On Whistling Girls and Jumping Sheep.", Undated (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 19)
- Teaching Contracts: Edith Cutting, 1938-1974 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 20)
- Yearbook: The Tioughmiogan, De Ruyter Central School, 1946 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 21)
- Yearbook: The Tioughmiogan, De Ruyter Central School, 1947 (Box 1 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 22)
- Large Black Scrapbook, 1958-1976 (Box 2 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 1)
- Harry S. Douglas. Wyoming County (New York) Historian. p. 38., 1958 December 16 (Item 1)
- Karen Keefe. Editor of The Parlor City Review. p. 47., 1976 July 21 (Item 2)
- G. Legman. From France: a request for Miss Cutting's help in locating ribald American and British ballads., Undated (Item 3)
- Small Brown Scrapbook, 1943-1951 (Box 2 (Edith Cutting Papers), Folder 3)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 1., 1943 December 9 (Item 1)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 2., 1944 January 6 (Item 2)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 4., 1943 June 23 (Item 3)
- Victor Reynolds. p. 6., 1944 December 5 (Item 4)
- Wayland D. Hand. Editor, American Folklore Society, Inc. p. 10., 1945 September 6 (Item 5)
- Jane Fennelly. Cornell University Press. p. 11., 1944 January 11 (Item 6)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 23., Undated (Item 7)
- Henry W. Shoemaker. Director, Pennsylvania State Library and Museum. p. 28., 1944 March 20 (Item 8)
- Henry W. Shoemaker. p. 32., 1944 April 11 (Item 9)
- Robert W. Crooks. Staff, New York Folklore Quarterly. p. 51., 1951 April 26 (Item 10)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 52., 1951 January 17 (Item 11)
- Harold W. Thompson. p. 55., 1951 January 19 (Item 12)
- Robert W. Crooks. p. 58., 1951 November 8 (Item 13)
- Victor Reynolds. p. 69., 1951 August 8 (Item 14)